Hello, everyone.
大家好。
Welcome to EnglishPod.
欢迎来到EnglishPod。
Today I'm here with Erika.
今天我和Erika一起。
Hi, Marco.
嗨，Marco。
And I'm Marco.
我是Marco。
And we're bringing you a great elementary lesson about a situation at an office.
我们为你带来一堂很棒的基础课，关于办公室里的一个场景。
That's true.
没错。
Today we're going to learn some phrases for asking for time off.
今天我们要学习一些请假用的短语。
Right.
对。
Asking for time off.
请假。
Or asking for leave.
或者申请休假。
Asking for leave.
申请休假。
Right.
对。
So we're going to give you some great phrases and vocabulary for when you want to ask for
所以我们会给你一些很好的短语和词汇，当你想要申请
leave.
休假时用。
So let's just listen to our dialogue today.
那么我们先来听今天的对话。
We're at an office where Liv wants some time off.
我们在一个办公室里，Liv想请几天假。
Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
McKenna先生，您有空吗？
I need to talk to you about something.
我需要和您谈点事。
Sure.
当然。
Liv, what can I do for you?
Liv，有什么事吗？
Well, I was just wondering.
嗯，我只是在想。
You see, I know I've used up all my vacation days this year, but my sister's getting married
您看，我知道我今年已经用完了所有年假，但我姐姐要结婚了，
and the wedding is overseas and, well...
婚礼在国外，而且……
You want to take some time off.
你想请几天假。
Is that right?
是吗？
Well, sir, I was just hoping I might be able to take some unpaid leave this year.
嗯，先生，我只是希望今年能请一些无薪假。
What dates are you planning on taking off?
你打算请哪几天？
I'll need at least two months' notice so that I can plan for your absence.
我需要至少两个月的通知，以便安排你不在时的工作。
I was thinking of taking off from September 1st until the 30th.
我想从9月1日休到30日。
Would you be okay with that?
您觉得可以吗？
Well, I guess so.
嗯，我想可以吧。
Well, it sounds like the boss wasn't too happy about Liv's request.
听起来老板对Liv的请求不太高兴。
Well, she wanted to take off for 30 days, so...
嗯，她想休30天，所以……
I guess that is a long time.
我想那确实挺长的。
That is a long time.
那确实很长。
I wish I could do that.
我希望我也能那样做。
Yeah.
是啊。
Okay, we have some great words for you today, so let's start with our language takeaway.
好的，今天我们有一些很棒的词汇，让我们从语言要点开始。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
Four words on our language takeaway today.
今天我们的语言要点有四个词。
Erika, why don't you tell us the first one?
Erika，你来说第一个吧？
The first word is vacation days.
第一个词是 vacation days。
Vacation days.
Vacation days。
So what are vacation days?
那么什么是 vacation days？
Basically, it's the number of personal leave days.
基本上，就是个人休假的天数。
So the number of days that you can take to go on vacation.
也就是你可以用来度假的天数。
How many vacation days do you have?
你有多少 vacation days？
Yeah, I think I have not so many.
嗯，我觉得我不太多。
I only have 10 vacation days.
我只有 10 天 vacation days。
10 vacation...
10 天假期……
Well, in some countries, 10 vacation days is normal.
嗯，在一些国家，10 天假期是正常的。
In another, I guess it's 10, 15, even 20, I've heard.
在另一些国家，我猜是 10 天、15 天，甚至 20 天，我听说过。
Yeah, yeah.
是的，是的。
Well...
嗯……
Vacation days.
Vacation days。
We can't take too many vacation days or else we won't make any more podcasts.
我们不能休太多假期，否则就做不了更多播客了。
Why don't we look at our second word?
我们来看看第二个词吧？
Overseas.
Overseas。
When you travel overseas, you travel over the ocean.
当你 travel overseas，就是跨洋旅行。
Over the ocean to another country.
跨过海洋去另一个国家。
Exactly.
没错。
Okay, overseas.
好的，overseas。
Okay, and our third word for language takeaway, unpaid leave.
好的，语言要点的第三个词，unpaid leave。
Unpaid leave.
Unpaid leave。
So this is time off without pay.
这是不带薪的休假。
Without pay.
不带薪。
Simple.
简单。
Right.
对。
Unpaid leave.
Unpaid leave。
And our last word, notice.
最后一个词，notice。
Notice.
Notice。
So we have some great examples on how we use notice and from these examples, I'm sure
我们有一些很好的例子说明如何使用 notice，从这些例子中，我肯定
you'll be able to understand exactly what they mean.
你就能准确理解他们的意思了。
Example one.
例子一。
If you want to quit your job, make sure you give enough notice.
如果你想辞职，一定要提前足够时间通知。
You'll need to tell us four weeks in advance.
你需要提前四周告诉我们。
Example two.
例子二。
You didn't give me enough notice about this project.
关于这个项目，你没有提前足够通知我。
I didn't have enough time to finish it.
我没有足够的时间完成它。
So when you give someone notice, you give them information in advance.
所以当你给某人通知时，就是提前给他们信息。
In advance, right.
提前，没错。
So if I want to take time off, I need to give my boss notice, advance information.
所以如果我想请假，我需要提前通知老板，也就是提前告知信息。
Right, 15 day notice or a 20 day notice, etc.
对，15天通知或20天通知等等。
Great, so that's our language takeaway for today.
太好了，这就是我们今天要学的语言点。
Now we are ready to listen to our dialogue a second time and this time it's going to
现在我们准备再听一遍对话，这次会
be really slow.
非常慢。
Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
McKenna先生，你有空吗？
I need to talk to you about something.
我需要和你谈点事。
Sure, Liv, what can I do for you?
当然，Liv，有什么可以帮你的？
Well, I was just wondering, you see, I know I've used up all my vacation days this year,
嗯，我只是在想，你看，我知道今年我已经用完了所有的年假，
but my sister is getting married and the wedding is overseas and well...
但我姐姐要结婚了，婚礼在海外，而且……
You want to take some time off, is that right?
你想请几天假，对吗？
Well, sir, I was just hoping that I might be able to take some unpaid leave this year.
嗯，先生，我只是希望今年能请一些无薪假。
What dates are you planning on taking off?
你打算休哪几天？
I'll need at least two months notice so that I can plan for your absence.
我需要至少两个月的通知，以便安排你不在时的工作。
I was thinking of taking off from September 1st until the 30th, would you be okay with
我打算从9月1日休到30日，您觉得可以吗？
that?
可以吗？
I guess so.
我想可以吧。
A lot of non-native English speakers sometimes feel quite nervous about asking their boss
很多非英语母语者在向老板请假时，有时会感到相当紧张，对吧？
for time off, hey?
请假？
Yeah, I guess it's a kind of a difficult subject.
是啊，我觉得这是个有点难开口的话题。
Yeah, but today we're going to teach you some great phrases that you can use next time you
是的，但今天我们要教你一些很棒的短语，下次你就能用了。
need to ask for some time off.
需要请几天假。
Great, so why don't we take a look at putting it together?
太好了，那我们来看看怎么把它组织起来？
Putting it together.
把它组织起来。
Okay, so on putting it together today, we're going to talk about some great phrases that
好的，今天在“组织起来”这个环节，我们要讨论一些很棒的短语，
you can use when approaching your boss.
当你去找老板时可以用到。
Yes, we heard Liv say this.
是的，我们听到丽芙说了这个。
Do you have a second?
你有空吗？
This is a nice way to make sure your boss isn't busy when you want to ask him something.
这是一种礼貌的方式，确保你老板不忙，然后你再问他事情。
Right, right, right, but we could also say this in two different ways.
对，对，对，但我们也可以用另外两种方式来说。
Let's listen.
我们来听一下。
Do you have a minute?
你有空吗？
I want to ask you something.
我想问你点事。
Do you have a sec?
你有空吗？
I need to talk to you.
我需要和你谈谈。
A great way to approach your boss.
一个接近老板的好方法。
Yeah, I love this phrase, do you have a sec?
是的，我喜欢这个短语，你有空吗？
Yeah, do you have a sec?
是的，你有空吗？
It's really natural.
这真的很自然。
Okay, so you've asked your boss for leave and you want to make sure that he agrees with
好的，你向老板请假，想确保他同意你的请求。
you.
你。
Yes, and this is how Liv did it.
是的，Liv就是这样做的。
Would you be okay with that?
你觉得这样可以吗？
This is a great pattern, and we've got two other examples of how you can use it.
这是一个很好的句型，我们还有另外两个例子说明如何使用它。
Example one.
例子一。
Are you alright with that?
你对此没意见吧？
Example two.
例子二。
Will you be okay with this?
你对此没问题吧？
Example three.
例子三。
I'm fine with that.
我没意见。
Okay, great examples, great patterns, really useful language.
好的，很好的例子，很好的句型，非常实用的语言。
Yes.
是的。
Okay, so now let's listen to our dialogue a third time.
好的，现在让我们第三次听对话。
Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
McKenna先生，您有空吗？
I need to talk to you about something.
我需要和您谈点事。
Sure, Liv, what can I do for you?
当然，Liv，有什么事吗？
Well, I was just wondering, you see, I know I've used up all my vacation days this year,
嗯，我只是在想，您知道，我今年已经用完了所有年假，
but my sister's getting married and the wedding is over season, well...
但我姐姐要结婚了，婚礼在旺季，嗯……
You want to take some time off, is that right?
你想请几天假，对吗？
Well, sir, I was just hoping I might be able to take some unpaid leave this year.
嗯，先生，我只是希望今年能请几天无薪假。
What dates are you planning on taking off?
你打算请哪几天假？
I'll need at least two months' notice so that I can plan for your absence.
我需要至少提前两个月通知，以便安排你不在时的工作。
I was thinking of taking off from September 1st until the 30th.
我想从9月1日请到30日。
Would you be okay with that?
您觉得这样可以吗？
Well, I guess so.
嗯，我想可以。
I really noticed how Liv in this dialogue used a lot of really polite language, hey?
我注意到Liv在这个对话中用了很多礼貌用语，对吧？
Yeah, I guess when you're talking to your boss, you really have to be respectful and
是的，我想和老板说话时，确实要尊重对方，
you have to use really polite language.
并且要用非常礼貌的语言。
What sort of things did she do to make herself seem more polite?
她做了哪些事情让自己显得更礼貌呢？
Well, she said a couple of interesting phrases, for example, well, I was just wondering.
嗯，她说了一些有趣的短语，比如，嗯，我只是在想。
Yeah, I was just wondering.
是啊，我只是在想。
Right, it's like, well, she's kind of setting up to ask for a favor or something.
对，就像，嗯，她好像在铺垫要请求帮忙之类的。
And she also used another phrase that I thought was interesting.
她还用了另一个我觉得有趣的短语。
Yeah, she also said, I was just hoping that.
是啊，她还说，我只是希望。
Yes.
是的。
Right, I was just hoping that maybe I could take some time off.
对，我只是希望也许我能请几天假。
Yeah, again, that sort of doesn't sound too strong, so it seems a bit more polite.
是啊，这种说法听起来不那么强硬，所以显得更礼貌一些。
Yeah, because if she said, well, I want to take some time off, that's too strong.
是啊，因为如果她说，嗯，我想请假，那就太强硬了。
Yeah, so I was just hoping.
是啊，所以用我只是希望。
And then, well, the boss says, okay, well, when do you want to leave?
然后，嗯，老板说，好的，嗯，你想什么时候走？
And she says, well, I was thinking of, right?
然后她说，嗯，我在想，对吧？
I was thinking of.
我在想。
Yeah.
嗯。
Again, if she would have said, I want to.
同样，如果她说，我想。
Yes.
是的。
Too strong, right?
太强硬了，对吧？
Yeah.
嗯。
In English, sometimes we are careful to not be too direct when we're asking for something,
在英语中，我们有时会注意在请求时不要太直接，
right?
对吧？
Right, yeah.
对，是的。
Because if you're too direct, you sound a little bit impolite.
因为如果你太直接，会显得有点不礼貌。
Yeah, you sound rude.
是啊，会显得粗鲁。
Yeah.
嗯。
Okay, so great tips and great things to take into consideration the next time you're talking
好的，这些是很棒的建议和值得注意的地方，下次你和老板说话时
into your boss.
可以记住。
All right, guys, we're out of time, but thanks for listening and be sure to check out our
好了，各位，时间到了，感谢收听，记得访问我们的
website EnglishPod.com.
网站 EnglishPod.com。
Right, where you can leave all your questions and comments and we'll be there to answer
对，在那里你可以留下所有问题和评论，我们会去回答
them.
它们。
But I guess until then, it's goodbye.
但我想在此之前，再见。
Bye.
再见。